Finding Aid for Department of Microbiology (University of Michigan) records
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Department of Microbiology (University of Michigan) records 1951-1979, 1959-1970
University of Michigan. Dept. of Microbiology.
(in 2 boxes)
1.5 linear feet
87146 Bimu C46 2
Collected historical information, including record of faculty research, 1890-1970, history of the department, and faculty bibliography; and correspondence and memoranda of chairmen, Walter J. Nungester and Frederick C. Neidhardt; also administrative files concerning faculty activities, fellowships, research projects, and student affairs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
A three volume history of the department was received in 1979. The administrative files were accessioned in September 1982. Donor number is 4846.
The collection is open to research.
The Department of Microbiology of the University of Michigan evolved from the Department of Hygiene and Physiological Chemistry, the Hygienic Laboratory, and the Department Of Bacteriology. It can trace its beginnings to 1981 when Dr. Victor C. Vaughan began teaching Sanitary Science as an elective course in the Department of Literature, Science, and the Arts. In 1887 he was appointed Professor of Hygiene and Physiological Chemistry and Director of the Hygienic Laboratory.
The Hygienic Laboratory was the first of its kind in the country, and had as its objectives teaching, research, and diagnostic service, Dr. Vaughan served as Director until 1909, and was succeeded by Dr. Frederick G. Novy, who held the position until 1935. Dr. Malcolm H. Soule was Director from 1935 to 1941, when the title of Director was abolished. The Department was associated with the Hygienic Laboratory until 1951.
The unit became known as the Department of Bacteriology in 1902; Dr. Novy served as its chairman until 1935, and was succeeded by Dr. Soule, who served until his death in 1951. Dr. Walter J. Nungester was Acting Chairman in 1951 1952, and Chairman from 1952 until his retirement in 1970. Dr. Frederick C. Neidhardt became chairman in September 1970. On July 1, 1963, the name of the department was changed to Department of Microbiology.
One of the early functions of the Department was to aid in the control of rabies. Because of the frequent outbreaks of rabies in the state, the Pasteur institute was set up as a part of the Hygienic Laboratory in 1903. The institute examined animals suspected of being infected with rabies, prepared vaccine, and administered the vaccine to persons who had been exposed to rabies. Examination of animals came to be the only function of the Institute, and the number of specimens began to decline. The Institute was abolished in 1959 because it was believed it no longer met a real need.
The bulk of the papers are from 1959-1970, years during which Dr. Nungester was chairman of the department. The papers have been arranged into three series; materials relating to the history and development of the department, correspondence and memoranda, and administrative files.
Materials relating to the development of the department include a history written by Dr. Novy, a biographical sketch of Dr. Novy, and summaries of data relating to faculty, students, course offerings, seminars, research and publications.
Correspondence and memoranda cover the years 1959-1971. Dr. Nungester's correspondence relates to the administration of the department and research in microbiology. Dr. Neidhardt's correspondence deals mainly with the transition period between his appointment as chairman and the actual beginning date of his tenure.
In the administrative files, the researcher will find copies of the alumni newsletter, annual reports, completed questionnaires, and financial records. There are also materials relating to faculty, students, research, outside speakers, and distinguished visitors to the department.
Subjects:
Neidhardt, Frederick C. (Frederick Carl), 1931-; Nungester, Walter James, 1901-; University of Michigan. Dept. of Bacteriology.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Research.
Contributors:
University of Michigan. Dept. of Microbiology.
- Materials relating to history of department
  - Microbiology, I,History of Department (Box 1)
  - Microbiology, II, Research 1890-1970 (Box 1)
  - Microbiology, III, Medical Student Teaching (Box 1)
  - Data Related to Department of Microbiology 1902-1966 (Box 1)
  - Bibliographies of Former Faculty 1965 (Box 1)
  - An Analysis of Course Curriculums and Major Fields of Interest of Recent Recipients of Doctoral Degrees from the University of Michigan's Department of Microbiology, report by Glenn Breitner and Frank Palmer May 1971 (Box 1)
  - Graduate Education in Microbiology and facilities of the department undated (Box 1)
- Correspondence and Memoranda
  - Walter J. Nungester
    - 1950 1959-1963 (Box 2)
    - 1965-1968 (1966 lacking) (Box 2)
    - 1969-1970 (Box 2)
    - Faculty Executive Committee, Phoenix Project, Correspondence and Minutes 1964-1966 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence relating to positions 1966-1967 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence relating to positions 1968-1969 (Box 2)
    - Copies of outgoing correspondence 1968 (Box 2)
    - Memoranda to staff 1962-1969 (Box 2)
  - Frederick C. Neidhardt
    - 1969 (Box 2)
    - 1970-1971 1974 (Box 2)
- Administrative Files
  - Alumni Newsletter
    - 1959, 1961-1966 (Box 2)
    - 1967-1969, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Annual Reports
    - Compliance Report, Animal Welfare Act 1969-1977 (Box 2)
    - Distribution of Cultures of Pathogenic Microorganisms 1968-1971 (Box 2)
  - Courses taught in department 1951-1973
  - Faculty
    - Faculty Effort Analysis 1967-1968 (Box 2)
    - Academic Personnel Activities Report 1970-1973
      - 1970-1971 (Box 2)
      - 1971-1972 (Box 2)
      - 1972-1973 (Box 2)
    - Publications (Box 2)
    - Rosters 1937-1975 (Box 2)
    - Teaching Assignments (Box 2)
  - Fellowships
    - Ford Foundation 1970 (Box 2)
    - W.K. Kellogg Foundation 1963, 1965 (Box 2)
    - National Science Foundation 1959-1960
  - Financial Records 1962-1970 (Box 2)
  - Graduate degrees awarded 1897-1970 (Box 2)
  - Novy Lecturers 1958-1966 (Box 2)
  - Pasteur Institute 1957-1959 (Box 2)
  - Personnel Rosters 1963-1969 (Box 2)
  - Questionnaires completed by department 1966-1969 (Box 2)
  - Randall, Harrison M., papers dealing with the use of infrared spectrophotometry
  - Research
    - Approved grant applications 1956-1964 (Box 2)
    - Research interests of faculty 1963-1967 (Box 2)
    - Research projects 1952-1954 (Box 2)
    - Research publications of faculty 1959-1966 (Box 2)
    - Student research-reports and evaluations 1960-1965 (Box 2)
  - Speakers brought to the department 1959-1966
  - Students
    - Graduate students 1964-1970 (Box 2)
    - Policy on stipends 1962-1967 (Box 2)
    - Student stipends 1958-1966 (Box 2)
    - Teaching Assistantship Assignments 1959-1967
  - Visitors to department 1959-1971 (Box 2)
  - Photographs, 2 envelopes (Box 2)
- Publications
  - Unit Publications
    - Brochures
      - Graduate Studies in Microbiology and Immunology, circa 1987 (Box 1)
      - Microbiology, undated (Box 1)
    - Newsletters
      - Alumni Letter, 1965, 1967, 2 folders (Box 1)